Guide to the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union Local 1 Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union Local 1 records
1933-1988
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
4307
4307-001
International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union.$bLocal 1 (Raymond, Wash.)
4.58 cubic feet 5 boxes
Records of the first International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union local chartered in the state of Washington
In 1937 the International Longshoremen's Association Local 38-92 (AFL) became the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (ILWU) Local 1, the first CIO local of the ILWU chartered in the state of Washington. ILWU Local 1 was based in Raymond, Washington (on Willapa Bay), and existed until it merged with Aberdeen Local 24 in 1976.
The records are arranged into three series:
Organizational files
Willapa Harbor Longshoremen's Benevolent Association
Pacific Coast Pensioner's Association
These records provide an important early record of CIO (Congress of Industrial Organizations) unions in the region.
Included are records of ILWU Local 1, minutes of other Washington locals' labor relations committees, and records of two benevolent associations -- the Willapa Harbor Longshoremen's Benevolent Association and the Pacific Coast Pensioner's Association -- that were intended to provide union workers with accident or retirement benefits. Individuals represented in the papers include ILWU Local 1 secretary Ralph W. Stark and Norman A. Mattson.
The records consist of minutes, correspondence, election material, newsletters, contracts and agreements, financial documents, conference and convention materials, publications, memorabilia, and ephemera.
The records are open to all users.
The records apparently were transferred to Aberdeen, Washington, when Local 1 and Aberdeen Local 24 merged in 1976. Jack Spurrell later took an interest in preserving them and brought them back to Raymond in 1988.
These records were given to the University of Washington Libraries by Jack Spurrell of Raymond, Washington, in July of 1991.
Information about the photographs that form part of this collection is available in the Special Collections division, University of Washington Libraries.
Mattson, Norman A.; Stark, Ralph W.; International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union.$bLocal 1 (Raymond, Wash.)$vArchives; Willapa Harbor Longshoremen's Benevolent Association; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Stevedores$xLabor unions$zWashington (State); Stevedores$xLabor unions$zWashington (State)$zRaymond; Industrial relations$zWashington (State); Fraternal organizations$zPacific Coast (U.S.); minutes; correspondence; conferences; ephemera; memorabilia; daybooks; Newsletters; Roll calls
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor Unions; Labor History; Washington (State); Artifacts; Scrapbooks
- Organizational files
  - Historical information, 1963-1986 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Organizational information, 1933-1988 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Organizational information, 1933-1988 (Box 5)
  - Minutes
    Begining in 1933, the minutes document the formational period of the organization following the waterfront strike of 1934. These minutes extend through 1968. Minutes from 1968 until the merger with the Aberdeen local in 1976, are presumed lost.
    - Longshoremen's Association, International, Local 38-92 (Raymond), Executive Board, 1947-1969 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Longshoremen's Association, International, Local 38-92 (Raymond), 1933-1968 (Box-folder 1/4-13)
    - ILWU Local 1 (Raymond) joint Labor Relations Committee meetings, 1970-1975 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - ILWU Local 1 (Raymond) stop work meetings, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 1/15-17)
    - ILWU Local 24 (Aberdeen) Labor Relations Committee, 1969-1974 (Box-folder 1/18-22)
    - ILWU Local 25 (Anacortes) Labor Relations Committee, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 1/23-27)
    - ILWU Local 7 (Bellingham) Labor Relations Committee, 1965-1974 (Box-folder 1/28-32)
    - ILWU Local 32 (Everett) Labor Relations Committee, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 1/33-37)
    - ILWU Local 47 (Olympia) Labor Relations Committee, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 1/38-42)
    - ILWU Local 27 (Port Angeles) Labor Relations Committee, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 1/43-46)
    - ILWU Local 51 (Port Gamble) Labor Relations Committee, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 1/47-51)
    - ILWU Local 19 (Seattle) Labor Relations Committee, 1964-1973 (Box-folder 2/1-12)
    - ILWU Local 23 (Tacoma) Labor Relations Committee, 1964-1974 (Box-folder 2/13-19)
    - ILWU Puget Sound Area Labor Relations Committee, 1967-1974 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - ILWU Puget Sound Council, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - ILWU Washington Area Labor Relations Committee, 1964-1973 (Box-folder 3/3-5)
    - ILWU Coast Labor Relations Committee, 1965 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Incoming letters
    - Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, International, Locals 4 through 142, 1965-1974 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, International, The Dispatcher, 1974 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, International, North West Regional Office, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, International, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, International, International Office, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, International, miscellaneous, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 3/12)
    - Pacific Maritime Association, Washington Area, 1965-1972 (Box-folder 3/13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1955-1975 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Outgoing letters, 1962-1975 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Elections, 1948-1971 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Newsletters, 1971 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - News releases, 1981 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Contracts and agreements, 1966-1975 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Petitions, undated (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Statements, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 3/21)
  - Financial reports, 1966, 1970 (Box-folder 3/22)
  - Reports-Grays Harbor annual report, 1966 (Box-folder 3/23)
  - Rules, undated (Box-folder 3/24)
  - Training material, undated (Box-folder 3/25-26)
  - Conference and convention materials
    - Pacific Coast District 29th annual conventions, 1936 (Box-folder 3/27)
    - Northwest Log Conference, 1970 (Box-folder 3/28)
    - ILWU 24th Biennial Convention, 1981 (Box-folder 3/29)
  - Publications, 1949-1987 (Box-folder 3/30-31)
  - Memorabilia
    - Leather workman's apron, undated (Box 5)
    - Banner-ILA Local 38-92, undated (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook-Longshore strike, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
  - Ephemera, undated (Box-folder 3/32)
  - Lists, 1975 (Box-folder 3/33)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 3/34)
  - Subject series
    - Labor relations, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Log export bill, 1973 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Medical benefits, undated (Box-folder 4/3-4)
    - Unemployment claims, undated (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Roll call, 1937-1968 (Box-folder 4/6-7)
  - Day book and roll call, 1935-1937 (Box-folder 4/8-9)
  - Day book, 1937-1946 (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Dues, 1933-1947 (Box-folder 4/11-12)
- Willapa Harbor Longshoremen's Benevolent Association, circa 1976-1982 (Box-folder 4/13-14)
- Pacific Coast Pensioner's Association, 1960-1981 (Box-folder 4/15-16)